<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sean Durfee</title>
    <description>Sean Durfee is a multi-disciplinary designer, front-end developer and project manager based out of Vancouver, British Columbia.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 15:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 15:12:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflections</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A reflection done at the end of the d.Studio course. Reflecting on what take-aways I learned during the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diversification, taking things in stride, asking for help, and realising the best designs are the obvious ones. I can’t really quantify how long each of these things took me to understand this term, but these are the things I attribute the completion and (by my standards) mild to moderate success of our deep dive and final deliverable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the term started out, our team’s ambition was really only matched by our naïvaite about what we were getting ourselves into. Starting out, we were lost. 100%. Either through a misguided sense of having prior experience or through a sense of instinct, I believed that for better or worse I was going to try and lead the team out of our pickle. I was so focused on this task, that talking to our client was something that I either forgot or was too afraid of damaging my pride to do. This was lesson number 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as we came away from our design brief, we all knew something was wrong — internally and externally. We quickly settled on two key issues: communication and figuring out what “design” actually was. The communication issue was the easy part and was quickly rectified by setting up regular meetings with both our client and with each other, having rolling milestones and deadlines, and splitting up tasks internally (lesson number part 2, lesson number 2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “learning design” might not be the right term for it, we flipped our thinking on its head. Instead of thinking along the lines of “what can we deliver”, we switched to “What does our client need and how can we deliver the best possible solution?” (lesson number 3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say the least the difference was night and day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began focusing on thinking outside of the box, looking for inspiration, and analysing our constraints. Overused ambiguous terms like “database” and “ecosystem” were thrown out and Simon Sinek’s “Why, How, What” that become our guiding mantra through every thinking stage. We found inspiration in odd places and came up with weird ideas (e.g. a certification program, inspired by the B Corp program) that didn’t pan out, but unlike before it all felt that it was ok. Instead of panicking over lost time, we just put it down as something to consider in the future. In the end, we had almost entirely lost our mentality of “what can we deliver” and were completely focused on how what we delivered would be beneficial for the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool story. So we did all these things. We sweat-blood-and-tears’ed together (not actually — I don’t think there was any bleeding or crying), but what am I — the greedy, self-centered person that I am — coming away with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Diversify. One person cannot do anywhere close to everything needed to do a project like this and multiple people within the same field don’t get the best results. Keeping tasks split up, playing to people’s strengths [aside: thank goodness for Ava’s ability to project manage – I don’t think I’ll ever be able to do that half as well as she can], and always bringing in new ideas are all things I will always be integrating into all my new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take things in stride. Big problems are scary. Before the Design Brief Debacle of 2015, we were so overwhelmed by the big elephant in the room of what we were going to do, that we got little to nothing done. Break down the problem through your desired method (Business Model Canvas, Six Years Six Months Six Weeks, Why How What, etc.) and focus on one small thing at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ask for help. Swallow your pride. Understanding the problem is 99% of the problem. If something isn’t working talk to people. Working in isolation does period not period work period.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realise the best designs are the obvious ones. Over thinking things is (apparently) my forté and something that I still need to work aggressively on. Remembering the heart of the problem or issue (by way of sticky notes or weeklies) is beyond critical to making sure the end product doesn’t suffer from feature bloat, gets off topic, or doesn’t help the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinning down exactly what it was that made this class so insightful and inspiring was hard to pin down. Sure, those things I learned were important, but beyond all that, I think it came down to how I perceived what design was. Going into the class, it was the harmonious combination between form and function, which to some degree I still believe is the case, but coming out of it has shown me it is also so, so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design isn’t just a visual thing restricted to graphic designers and the circle-jerk that is Dribbble and Behance. Design is Public, Playground Inc., Dossier, Apple, and Facebook. Design is taking the babbling, incoherent vision of a client (or your own dream, class project, manager, etc) and turning it into something so harmonious that the client says, “Oh. Yeah, of course”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is good design.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/reflections</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/reflections</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Entrepreneurship</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Starting a business is like starting a new relationship. The series of emotions and ideas follow identical patterns, but unlike relationships many of you are obstinately convinced that being an entrepreneur is a near impossible feat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it’s because I’m socially inept on a level that would make introverts feel comfortable, but I passionately believe that being an innovator requires as much care as being in a relationship. You’re probably thinking, that’s all well and good, but those two things are most certainly not the same thing. Come on, get your shit together. Bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-relationship-can-be-broken-down-into-five-phases&quot;&gt;A relationship can be broken down into five phases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You connect with someone on an emotional or physical level.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You spend some time with that person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Things start to get serious, and after a while, you commit yourself to that person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, something fails horribly. Your heart explodes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the ice cream, booze, and binge watching of Friends, you pick up the pieces and the whole cycle repeats itself.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all been there, right? And have come out on the other side with more experience, more stories, and—after some time, hopefully—a few lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;those-phases-compared-to-starting-a-business&quot;&gt;Those phases compared to starting a business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You find an idea that you like so you flirt with it for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You gage interest, and start prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You spend some more time with your idea; get to know it further.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re lucky, things fall into place and start to get more serious. You find yourself working 80-hour weeks—but are loving it, because it leaves you feeling satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As most good things often do, a part of it will break. Something will fail. You walk away with your lessons, the experiences, and pride in the knowledge that you tried. The next idea will come along and you’ll try again; you’ll keep learning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See? Not that different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;IT SHOULD BE A LOVE AFFAIR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Innovator” or “entrepreneur” are loaded titles that come with a whole slew of preconceptions and judgements. Let’s put those aside for a moment. People in committed and healthy relationships don’t receive titles or prestige, but they still care enough to make sure the relationship worked and lasted. Innovators and entrepreneurs are just people who cared enough about an idea to see it come into reality. They knew that failure was a possibility, but put themselves out there for the world to see anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat your ideas with the same respect you give your partner. Know that everything will not always work out and you cannot possibly please everyone, but having the courage, strength, devotion, and confidence to try? That’s innovation. Being an entrepreneur is just putting the idea out into the world and that is something that everyone can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, take a chance on that idea you were flirting with. Be courageous and embrace failure. Be daring and do your best work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This appeared in Class Magazine on December 16, 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;http://classmagazine.ca/2015/12/16/love-lust-business-plans-the-5-phases-of-starting-up-in-your-twenties/&quot;&gt;over here&lt;/a&gt; and was edited by the lovely Sasha Curry of West Coast Social.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/entrepreneurship</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/entrepreneurship</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Design Thinking</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;-thinking&quot;&gt;∆ Thinking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design thinking is not something that easily comes to people, myself included. My own little adventure in design has by no means been extensive or trying. In fact, I have absolutely no basis for being able to talk about this, but hey it’s a learning process. So maybe by writing about how my process has come together and how I can further critique it means that maybe I can help others get on their own track faster? We’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-watch-your-approach&quot;&gt;Step 1: Watch your approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some very wise sages have oft said the importance of looking to the past to understand the present and future. This means looking at how customers have been treated in the past and how you can improve that. Or maybe if you are working for a client, this might mean understanding how their business has been functioning in the past and analyzing what trends and themes brought them to where they are today. Recognizing the themes and trends across products, ideas, and styles gives you insight into the market, but more importantly how people think. Sitting down with a client and talking about their past and their vision for the future is always the first thing that I do. Don’t even try to start working on things until this is done. Not only does it give me context for where my work is going to go, but it is a good indicator of what I’m getting myself into. If the client can’t speak to their past and why they are looking for change, that should be a warning flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-problems-are-hard-dont-make-them-harder&quot;&gt;Step 2: Problems are hard, don’t make them harder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at a new project is terrifying. The more you think about it, the more you realize how much you have to do, how little time you have, and how many constraints you have. After a little hyperventilating, six cups of coffee, and a long swim, dive right in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quantify what you have to do.
There are so many good tools out there to do this, it’s amazing. Sticky notes to mood boards; creative briefs to the Business Model Canvas; group pow-wows to crazy ideas — really it doesn’t matter which you choose. I’ve had success with most of these and have yet to try the others, but they all do the same thing: give you a plan of attack and define the terms you’re working under. From there it’s just execution and that’s the easy part. I’m all for going for going on aimless bike rides, but a casual bike ride isn’t a 200 hour time investment — so have a plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-make-friends&quot;&gt;Step 3: Make friends&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaborate with people that aren’t your client. Holy dear flying spaghetti monster find people to collaborate with. This took me an embarrassingly long time to figure out. Being in a setting where you can bounce ideas off of people — ideally outside of your immediate bubble — is 100% guaranteed to make your design thinking strategy better. The ideas might be “bad” or “silly”, but will always be able to contribute something to the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Step 4: Never think you are done learning
If I had a dollar for the number of times that I’ve thought to myself, “I know how to [x]! Cool! Implementing this will be easy” I would be able to pay rent for a few months. If you think there is only one way to do something, that one idea is superior, or you’ve read enough about something you’re gonna have a bad time. Consider your point of view temporary. Keep reading, keep learning, keep trying, and never stop failing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-5-dont-trust-advice-from-people-who-say-they-changed-their-entire-life-in-any-number-of-easy-secret-or-tricky-steps&quot;&gt;Step 5: Don’t trust advice from people who say they changed their entire life in any number of “easy”, “secret”, or “tricky” steps.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They usually have no idea what they’re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put this in the context of our recent class project, it’s been an interesting learning experience. In a lot of ways, the material covered in the course has been an exercise in reinforced learning and putting labels on things that I previously just did without knowing that it was a pre-established method. It has certainly been very encouraging that I haven’t been approaching things completely incorrectly. More than that though, it has shown me that I have a lot of room for improvement and expansion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally my approach to a project is a somewhat hybridized method between Lockwood’s and Raney and Jaooby’s methods, but with some outside influence. This has largely consisted of breaking down the problem, getting inspired, prototyping, and constantly launching, tweaking, and relaunching. Working within the course has been a little different however. Being a freelancer, I’m largely used to working alone (hence the slow learning referenced in step 3) and working in the collaborative setting of the design studio has taught me two important things, especially with my leadership style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideas evolve quickly, but sometimes a little too quickly.
Part of my leadership style that I pride myself on (but sometimes bemoan) is getting everyone on board with an idea before moving forward. When working with really small teams (two or four), this usually means bouncing a few ideas off of each other, coming to a decision collectively and moving forward. Yet in the instance of the class, on-boarding such a diverse group is much harder. At this point, I’m not sure how I should proceed with this knowledge, but is something that I need to keep in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Harnessing the big picture is hard.
When reading through the Ten Faces post, I self-identified as a hybrid between a Cross-Pollinator and a Hurdler, but (as previously mentioned) most of my leadership experience is not in leading teams across projects, so I am interested to see how both of these play into the group dynamic as the term goes on. Or maybe they won’t and I’ve got some seriously bad cognitive bias.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/design-thinking/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/design-thinking/</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
